Now let's look at three applications
where we use the type of methods that you
will learn in this course and apply them
to real sensor observations.
This first example concerns tracking vehicles
using observations from a mono camera
and comes from this paper by Samuel Scheidegger in 2018.
The aim is to estimate the 3D position and velocity
of vehicles from a sequence of images.
Much in the same way as we did in our previous illustration,
but with actual camera observations.
The observations that are used come
from a convolutional neural network
which is trained to detect vehicles
and to report a 2D bounding box of the vehicles in the image,
as illustrated by these colored boxes,
as well as the distance to the object.
As we discussed previously, using a single camera,
we cannot directly measure the distance to the vehicle.
The distance reported by the network is therefore, instead,
based on learned scale and appearance cues,
and can sometimes be a bit noisy.
However, by filtering these observations
in a so-called unscented Kalman filter, which
you will learn about in this course,
we can get better and less noisy estimates
of where the vehicles are.
So what we will see to the left is the original image
where the bounding boxes of the detected vehicles
are shown in separate colors.
To the right is a bird's eye view of the situation,
centered at the camera.
The detection from the camera is shown as white stars.
And the result of our filter is shown as these colored ellipses
with the same color as the bounding boxes in the image.
And the plus in the middle here indicates our estimated
position.
And the star is the actual positions of the vehicles.
So ideally, we want our estimate, the plus markers,
to be as close as possible to the true position
of the vehicles, the stars, which
would mean that our guess of where the vehicle is,
is accurate.
Now, when we start playing the video,
we will also illustrate the trace of the vehicle
to show the filtered and true vehicle trajectories over time.
Now, let's view the result. What we
see here is that our filter manages
to filter the noisy detections from the camera
and over time gets more and more certain about the position
of the vehicles.
Pretty nice, right?
The next example that we're going to look at
is related to the geometry of the road ahead of our host
vehicle.
This work was published in this paper from 2016,
where we used observations from a radar and a camera
to try to estimate the geometry or shape of the road
up to 200 meters ahead of our host vehicle
in highway scenarios.
Now from the camera, we get information
about the shape of the lane markings, of the current lane.
These are shown here as red dashed lines.
Typically, the camera is able to detect
the lane markings up to roughly 50 to 60 meters,
but sometimes shorter.
The length of these lines indicate
how far ahead the lane geometry from the camera is valid.
From the radar, we mainly get two things.
First, we get the relative position and velocity
of other vehicles.
These are shown here as these blue dots
where the arrow indicates the velocity vector.
The second thing that we get is stationary detections
from the roadside objects, such as guardrails or barriers,
as shown here.
So how can we use this to estimate
the geometry of the road?
Well, the lane markings coming from the camera
is directly related to the shape of the road, right?
But in best case, it's only valid up to roughly 50,
60 meters, which is not enough.
The radar, on the other hand, can see much further
and typically reports objects up to 200 meters or more.
However, the radar cannot measure the geometry
of the road directly.
What it can do is to measure the position and velocity
of the other vehicles that are traveling on the road.
And as they are traveling on the road,
their velocity vector should be roughly parallel to the road,
right?
Similarly, the reflection from the guardrail shown here
should also align and be roughly parallel to the road as well.
So what we have done is to construct sensor models
saying that a camera can measure the road up to 50, 60 meters,
that the vehicles that are detected by the radar
should drive approximately parallel to the road.
If we are able to detect a guardrail,
this guardrail should be approximately
parallel to the road as well.
Now, if we assume that we can describe
the shape of the road using a so-called clothoid spline, so
a mathematical model of the road geometry,
we can then estimate the parameters
of this spline using our sensor models
and our observations in an unscented Kalman filter.
The resulting clothoid spline is shown here
as this magenta-colored line, where
our uncertainty in the shape of the road
is shown as these error ellipses at the splinoids.
The black lines here indicate that we
have detected a guardrail at these distances
perpendicular to the road.
The blue dots here is the ground truth position
of the middle of the host lane, which
is what we like to describe.
We will plot the results having our host vehicle at the origin,
always pointing to the right.
So if we run our filter, it could look something like this.
Here we see that we're able to fairly accurately describe
the shape of the road at also far distances,
by including information about the direction in which
the leading vehicles are traveling
and the shape of the detected guardrails.
What's happening here is that we get limited information
about the shape of the road at 200 meters,
so we assume that the road is still
bending when it's actually starting to straighten out.
We should also note that our uncertainty increases here.
Once we get new observations telling the filter
that the road has straightened out, our filter quickly adapts.
The third example of how we can use the methods that you will
learn in this course is related to the problem
of self-localization.
Let's say that we have an autonomous vehicle which
should navigate on its own in this type of city environment.
Well, it would surely be beneficial to have
some kind of map to navigate by, and that our vehicle is
able to position itself in this map, such
that it knows when it's time to make
a right at this intersection here, for example.
One possible such map could be a semantic 3D point cloud map.
Now this is a 3D point cloud where
each point is labeled by the semantic class of the object
at that specific position.
This label could, for example, be road, sidewalk, building,
tree, and so on.
This type of map can be constructed
from a sequence of semantically segmented street view images
using structure from motion and multiview stereo algorithms.
But this is not the focus of this course.
So for our little piece of a city,
the map could look something like this.
So here we see that we have points labeled
as road, sidewalk, buildings, trees, vegetation,
and some other smaller classes.
So let's now assume that this is our map
and that we would like to position ourself in this map.
Now, we've said that this is a 3D point cloud map, which
means that each point has a 3D position
and that we can view this map from any post, that is,
position and heading of our host vehicle.
The idea of how to localize our vehicle in this type of map
is simple.
What we will present here is based on this paper
by Erik Stenborg et al. from 2018.
Now, assume that we have a camera on our vehicle
that can observe this scene.
We can then try to align our pose such
that if we project our semantic 3D map onto our camera image,
our building points will fall on buildings
and our tree points will land on trees, and so on.
Now here is one such image from a camera
observing the same scene as our map,
where we have semantically labeled each pixel in the image
with the same classes that we have in our map.
We do this by using a deep convolutional neural
network that takes an ordinary image as input,
and outputs a semantic label of each pixel.
In the image to the right, we have
overlaid the semantic image on the original image where
we can see that the network manages to fairly well label
each pixel.
Additionally, a subset of our map points
are projected onto our image.
And as we can see, our black building points
fall on buildings and our green tree points land
on trees, for example.
This would indicate that the pose that we
have used to project our map onto our image
matches well with the actual pose of the camera.
So how can we use this to position our autonomous
vehicle?
Well, one way is to use a so-called particle
filter, which we will learn all about in this course.
Using a particle filter, we would
represent the pose of our vehicle, so position
and heading, using a whole bunch of more or less randomly chosen
particles.
Now, each particle-- here shown in yellow in the figure
to the left--
describes one possible pose of our vehicle, or actually
a whole vehicle trajectory.
But let us not focus on that right now.
Each particle is then rated by how well
it explains our observations.
So how well a projection of our map, using that particles pose,
matches with our semantically segmented images.
The particle that matches the best will then
get a high score and the particles
where the projected map and the semantic segmentation matches
poorly will get a low score.
When we now run our particle filter,
we will see the position of the particles in yellow
in this bird's eye view of our semantic 3D point cloud map
to the left.
And to the right, we will see the semantic segmentation
of our current image and the projected map points
for the best scoring particle.
The green triangle to the left represents the actual position
of the vehicle.
What we can see with this type of filter
is that our uncertainty is described
by how spread out our particles are,
which is a bit different than the other methods
that we will learn in this course.