The theory, methods, and algorithms
used to do sensor fusion and nonlinear filtering
relies heavily on mathematical statistics.
In order to follow this course, we therefore
recommend that you have a good understanding
of some basic statistical concepts.
To help you out, we have put together this set of lectures
where we'll go through the most important concepts on a fairly
high level.
Our hope is that what we present here
is not new to you, but rather a refresher on things
that you already know.
However, if you feel that some of these concepts that we
present here are unfamiliar to you,
we would highly recommend that you take some time
and read up on these.
In this first lecture, we're going
to discuss random variables.
When we do nonlinear filtering, we
need them to describe the quantity
that we're interested in, for example,
the position of a vehicle.
We also need random variables to describe the observations
that we want to filter.
To describe our random variables,
we'd use the so-called probability mass function
for discrete-valued random variables
and a so-called probability density function
for continuous valued random variables.
Let's start by looking at discrete-valued random
variables, for which we describe their properties using
a Probability Mass Function, or pmf for short.
Now, the probability mass function
of a discrete-valued random variable is, in this course,
denoted as Pr of z, or just P of z.
But we will mostly be using this notation in this course.
Note also that we are using braces here
to indicate that z is a discrete-valued random
variable.
Now, our probability mass function
need to have the following properties in order
to be proper probability mass functions.
First, the probability that our discrete-valued random variable
z is equal to some integral value
i, which is written like this, needs
to be greater than or equal to 0.
Now, one way to view this value here
is if we collect many values of z,
the fraction of these that are equal to i
is given by this number here.
And this needs to hold for all values of i.
The second property of our probability mass function
is that if we sum over all values of z,
this sum needs to be 1.
That is, the probability that z takes any value needs to be 1.
We can also note that as a consequence of these two,
we cannot have a probability mass for a value i that is
greater than 1, which seems to be reasonable, right?
Now if we look at this use in the example of a fair dice,
the probability mass function for the face value
that I would get if we rolled the dice can
be written like this.
So the dice has six faces with a value 1
through 6, which each is equally probable.
So the probability that z is i is equal to 1/6,
if i is equal to 1, 2, and so on up to 6, and 0 otherwise.
If we visualize this pmf, it will look something
like this, where we only have probability
mass for discrete values.
I would encourage you to verify for yourself
that this is a pmf here which has both of these properties
here, and that you understand why that is.
Now let's look at a corresponding description
for continuous-valued random variables, which
we call the Probability Density Function, or pdf for short.
So the probability density function
of a continuous-valued random variable
is denoted as lowercase p of z.
And again, the probability density of any value of z
needs to be greater or equal to 0.
And if we integrate p of z over all values of z,
this integral needs to be 1.
Now again, the interpretation of this
is that the probability that z takes some value always
needs to be 1.
However, it does not follow that p of z has to be lower than 1
for all values of z, as in the discrete case.
We only require that it should integrate to 1.
So the probability density for some value of z
could actually be greater than 1.
Let's look at an example of a continuous-valued random
variable z which is uniformly distributed between 0 and 2 pi.
So here z could, for example, be a stochastic angle.
The pdf of z can then be written like this,
where we have 1 over 2 pi if z is within the interval of 0
to 2 pi and 0 otherwise.
Now, we get 1 over 2 pi here, as all angles are equally
probable in a uniform distribution
and the size of the interval is 2 pi.
So 1 over 2 pi.
If we visualize this density, it will look something like this.
If we were to relate the probability mass
function to the probability density function,
we can consider the discrete-valued random variable
describing the event that z is in some interval A.
So we have some interval here which we call A.
And we want to know if z is within this interval.
Now, the probability mass that z is in this interval
can be written like this.
So z is in A and can be calculated by integrating pdf
over the interval A. So this is the integral of the pdf.
So in this case, the pmf is the integral of the pdf.