In this course, we're very interested in how
the distribution of two or more random variables
depend on each other.
We do this by mainly considering the so-called conditional
and joint distributions.
Additionally, we are also interested in knowing
the so-called marginal distribution, which
is the isolated distribution of a single random variable, where
we have removed the influence of all the other variables.
All of these are central in their understanding
of our nonlinear filtering methods.
In this lecture, we will define these distributions
and look at how they are related to each other.
We will also look at an illustrative toy
example, including all of these distributions.
We start by looking at conditional distributions,
which are indispensable components in sensor fusion,
filtering, and Bayesian estimation, in general.
And we define them like this--
let x and z be two random variables, with the joint pdf p
of x comma z, so p of x and z.
Now the conditional density function,
which you read as the probability density of z
given x is defined through the so-called product rule, which
states that the joint probability of x and z
can be written as a product of these two densities--
so the conditional density of z given
x times the marginal distribution of x.
This implies that for possible values
of x, that is, values of x which has non-zero probability
density, we can write the conditional density of z
given x as the ratio between the joint probability of x and z
divided by the marginal of x.
So we normalize the joint distribution of x and z
with a probability of x to get the conditional density of z
given x.
Now, typically, we view this here as a function of z,
and that x is just some known constant value.
In our case, this is usually the value of some measurement
that we have already observed.
To make this a bit more obvious, we
could rewrite this expression as p of z
where x is equal to some x prime--
so x prime is just some constant value.
Then we get p of x prime and z divided by p of x prime.
Now, as x prime is just some constant, then p
of x prime is also some constant.
And p of x prime comma z now only
depend really on z, as x is some constant.
So we can view this as a parameter in this function
here.
So, in principle, we take a joint probability density
of p of x prime and z, and then normalize it
with this constant of the probability density of x prime.
Now, as we're typically interested in this
as a function of z, in many cases, it's beneficial for us
to view this as proportional to the joint density.
So the conclusion here is that the conditional density of z
given x is proportional to the joint density where we have
fixed one of the dimensions-- x, in this case--
and then view it as a function of z.
And the interpretation here is that p of z
given x describes the distribution of z given
that x is known.
So we don't have any uncertainty about x anymore-- x
is equal to x prime, in this case.
We know this.
Let's look at the toy example to hopefully make
things a bit more clear.
In this toy example, Sara decides every day
how many pieces of candy she can have for an after-lunch snack.
Now to make things a bit more interesting,
she decides how many candies she gets
at random using the intricate scheme involving both tossing
a coin and rolling dice.
So with 40% probability, she tosses a coin
where if it end up at heads, means that she
will get 1 piece of candy.
And if it gets tails, it means that she
will get 0 pieces of candy.
However, with 60% probability, she
throws a dice, and whatever the number on the dice is,
that will be how many candies she will get that day.
Now, if we let z denote the number of candies
that she eats, what is, then, the conditional probability
that she eats i candies, given that Sara tosses a coin
or that she throws a dice.
Well, let's look at the conditional probability here.
So we condition on that Sara tosses a coin,
so we have no uncertainty regarding which method
that she uses to determine how many candies that she gets.
Now if we know that she tosses a coin,
we also know that with 50% probability,
she will get one piece of candy, and with 50% probability,
she will get zero pieces of candy.
With this information, we can describe
this conditional density--
or conditional probability-- like this.
We'll have 0.5 probability that she will get 1 or 0 candies.
And then 0% probability that she will get
any other number of candies.
Similarly, if we know that she throws a dice,
the only uncertainty that we have left
is regarding the face value of the dice.
If she rolls a 1, she gets 1 candy.
If she rolls a 2, she gets 2 pieces, and so on.
And as she has a fair dice, she has equal probability
of getting 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, or 6 pieces of candy.
And the probability of this is 1 over 6.
We can just express this conditional probability
like this.
So 1 over 6 probability, if i is equal to 1, 2, and so forth, up
to 6, and 0 probability otherwise.
The next thing that we will look at
is marginal distributions, which we
get by using the law of total probability.
Now there are many important results
in nonlinear filtering that is obtained
from the law of total probability.
So I highly recommend that you get
yourself familiarized with it.
Now the law of total probability order sum rule
is defined like this.
Let's say that we, again, have two random variables-- so x
and z-- which has some joint distribution, like this
in the discrete case, or like this in the continuous case.
So if x takes values in sum set, Sx, the law
of total probability states that the marginal distribution of z,
which we write like this in the discrete case,
and like this in the continuous case,
can be found from the joint distribution
by summing over all the possible values of x
in the discrete case, or integrating
over all the possible values of x in the continuous case.
We can interpret this as we are marginalizing out
the influence of x by summing or integrating
over all possible values of x.
So what is left is the marginal probability distribution
that now only depends on z, in this case.
So we're marginalizing out x from these joint distributions.
Now there's also a common and equivalent way
of expressing the law of total probability, and that,
by splitting these joint probabilities using the product
rule into these two factors, like this.
So these two are equivalent forms of the same law.
So let's return to the candy example
and try to find a marginal distribution of how
many candies that Sara gets, without caring
about how she actually got him.
So to calculate these marginal pmf how many candies Sara gets,
we used the law of total probability
to sum over all possible ways that Sara chooses
how many candies that she gets, either by tossing a coin
or throwing a dice, and then summing
over this joint distribution of z and x.
Note that this is just a joint distribution of z and x.
Additionally, remember that she tosses
a coin with 40% probability, and that she throws
a dice with 60% probability.
Now I would encourage you to post a video here and try
to calculate this marginal distribution on your own.
As a hint, I would suggest that you first
calculate the joint probability of z
and x by filling out this table here,
and using this expression here for the joint probability.
Additional things that I would like
for you to consider while doing this
is, how can we go from the joint distribution
to the marginal distribution by using this table here?
And can we also find the conditional distributions
in this table?
If you pause now and try to answer these questions
on your own, I will go through the answers with you
when you get back.
So now I hope that you've been able to solve this.
Now what I would do is that I would start by calculating
this joint probability here.
And we know that we can express this joint probability using
the product through like this.
So if we look at this cell here, we
have the probability that she tosses a coin
and gets 0 pieces of candy.
Now the probability of getting no candies, if we condition on
that she tosses a coin is 0.5.
And the probability that she tosses a coin
from the first place is 40%, or 0.4.
So here we have 0.5 times 0.4, which is 0.2.
Now the probability that she tosses a coin
and gets 1 piece of candy is the same, so we also have 0.2 here.
However, she cannot get more than 1 piece of candy if she
tosses a coin, so all of these probabilities here are 0.
Similarly, if we look at the probability of throwing a dice
and getting a certain number of candies,
she has equal probability of getting 1, 2, 3, 4, or 5,
or 6 pieces of candy, which is 1 over 6
for this conditional probability here, where we condition on
that she is throwing a dice.
And the probability of throwing a dice is 0.6.
So all of these values here are 1 over 6 times
0.6, which is 0.1.
And there is 0 probability of throwing the dice
and getting 0 pieces of candies--
that should be 0 here.
So how do we go from the joint probability
here to the marginal probability of z?
Well, our aim is to get the probability of just z,
and by using the law of total probability,
we sum out the dependency on x by fixing z and summing
over all possible values of x.
And if we look at this table here,
we do this by looking at one of the columns
here and then summing over the rows.
So we get the marginal probability of z
by summing over the rows for each column.
And while we're at it, we might as well
verify that this holds true for the marginal distribution of p
of x, which we get for each row by summing over the columns,
instead, in this table.
Now we see we get 0.4 for tossing
a coin, which seems reasonable.
And we get 0.6 for throwing the dice, which
also seems reasonable.
This is what we expected from the beginning.
Now we're also promised that we could
find these conditional distributions in this table
here.
So this conditional distribution here-- the distribution
of pieces of candy that Sara gets,
given that we condition on the method that Sara uses.
And, as I mentioned before, we typically
view this as a function of z for a fixed value
on x, which is known.
Now if we look at this table here, for a fixed value of x,
let's say that Sara tosses a coin,
we can see that this row here is proportional
to the marginal distribution of pieces of candy that Sara gets,
given that she tosses a coin.
And we can also see that the proportionality constant
that we need to divide by in order for this
to be a proper density is 0.4, which is the probability
that Sara tosses a coin.
Similarly, this row here is then the conditional probability
of z given that Sara throws a dice.
And, again, the proportionality of the constant
we get by summing over all of these
is 0.6, which is the marginal distribution
that Sara throws a dice.
Now we can also get the marginal distribution
of x given that she gets a certain piece of candy,
which we then find on the columns here.
So this, for example, is then proportional to the probability
of x, given that she gets 5 pieces of candy.