In this lecture, we're going to go
through three of the most important basic tools
that we're going to use throughout this course.
And that is expectation, covariance,
and the Gaussian distribution.
That actually sounds like the title of a movie
that I would watch.
Now, anyway, the single most important distribution
for sensor fusion and nonlinear filtering
is the Gaussian distribution.
In many cases, our goal is to describe our results
using the mean vector or expected value
and the covariance matrix of a Gaussian distribution.
And if our result is not Gaussian,
we anyway tend to approximate our results using the mean
and covariance of this non-Gaussian distribution,
even though these do not fully capture all the facets
of our actual distribution.
So as we said, probability distributions
are also characterized by their mean vectors
and covariance matrices.
So how do we calculate this?
Well, the expected value or mean of an m-dimensional random
vector x, defined like this, is the expected value of x.
Now, the expectation of x is defined
as an integral of the vector x weighted by the probability
density of that vector.
So what we have here is that for values
of x which have high probability density
will influence our expected value
more than values of x which have low probability density.
Often we denote this mean vector here as either mu, or x bar
in this case.
And we call this the first moment of p of x.
Now, the notation here is simply shorthand that we
integrated from minus infinity to infinity
for all the dimensions of x.
So that was the expected value.
Now, the covariance of x or the second central moment
of p of x is written like this and is defined
as the expectation of x minus its mean times the same thing
transposed.
Now, we can view this factor here
as the distance between x and its mean,
that is, how much does x spread around its mean value?
Now, if we write it like this, we
assume that x is a column vector,
as we will do throughout the whole of this course,
as this here, the product here, should be an outer product.
That is, we have a tall matrix times a wide matrix.
So this product here is an m by m squared matrix, which
is symmetric and positive semidefinite, as this
is a square here.
So it needs to be positive semidefinite.
So that is the definition of the covariance matrix
of a random variable x.
Now, for discrete-valued random variables,
the above integrals are then replaced
by corresponding summations.
So we have summation here instead.
So let us look a bit more into how
we can interpret this covariance matrix using an example where
we have independent samples from a zero-mean two-dimensional
random vector x, which has the components x1 and x2.
Now, our samples are plotted in red here in this figure.
The question is if you can guess the covariance matrix
of x using these samples here.
Now, to help you out a bit, we have also
plotted to one standard deviation
and three standard deviation contours
of the distribution of x.
So we have three sigma contour here,
and we have one sigma contour here.
Additionally, we can mention that the covariance
of a two-dimensional random variable
has the following structure.
So the covariance of x can be written like this, where
sigma 1 is the standard deviation of x1 and sigma 2
is the standard deviation of x2.
And the factor rho here is what's
called a correlation factor.
So what do you think the covariance of x is?
I would encourage you to pause the video here and think
about this yourself for a couple of minutes.
And then we can go through the results together.
So as I mentioned, the covariance matrix
is a measure for how the samples of a random vector
have spread around its mean.
Now, as x is a zero-mean random vector,
its mean is located here at 0, 0.
And if we look at the structure of the covariance matrix
that we'll find here, we see that we basically
need to find the standard deviation of x1 and x2
plus the correlation factor rho.
Now, the standard deviation of x1 and x2
can be found by projecting this one sigma
contour onto both dimensions here and then
looking at the distance between the projected
contour and the mean.
So if we do this, we get sigma 1 and sigma 2
approximately equal to 1.4.
So we can start filling in our covariance matrix here.
So what about the correlation factor?
So we know that the correlation factor
is a value between minus 1 and 1 that tells us how correlated
two random variables are.
If the correlation factor is, for example, 1,
the two random variables are fully positively correlated,
meaning that x1 here, for example,
is a deterministic positive function of x2, and vice versa.
Now, if we look at our samples, we
see that there is quite a significant positive
correlation here.
So if we have a high value on x1,
there's a high probability that x2 also has a high value.
But it's definitely not a deterministic mapping, right,
as if it were, all the samples here would collapse and fall
on the line like this.
But that's not the case, right?
So we have some spread around us.
So this would mean rho equal to 1,
if all the samples were on this line.
Now in this case, I would say that the correlation
is somewhere around 0.9.
So we have 0.9 here.
Putting this together, we get a final guess
for our covariance matrix, which is--
so the variance in each dimension is around 2.
And we have a cross-covariance of 1.8.
So does this match what you guessed?
So if we look at the covariance matrix for a random variable,
it will tell us both the variance
in the different dimensions, but it will also
tell us how correlated the different dimensions are.
So we have a cross-covariance of 1.8 here between x1 and x2.
And this information is something
that is used extensively in sensor fusion and nonlinear
filtering, which we will see later in this course.
Sometimes we're interested in finding
the expected value of a random variable numerically.
Perhaps we are not able to solve the involved integrals
explicitly, or more commonly, when we do not actually
know the underlying distribution but have access
to a large number of samples from it.
So in this case, we can use the law of large numbers, which
states that sample averages converge
to expected values for large sample sizes.
Now, if x1, x2, and so on are independent and identically
distributed random variables, distributed according
to some distribution p of x, then the sample average,
that is, we sum all the samples and divide
by the number of samples, will converge
to the actual expected value of x
under p of x if we let the number of samples
grow to infinity.
Now, we can think of this as throwing a dice many times,
where each roll of the dice would generate
a new, independent, and identically distributed
sample from a distribution of dice face values.
If we do this sufficiently many times,
eventually the average face value
converges to expected value, which we can
calculate to be 3.5, like this.
So this is a way to numerically calculate expected values.
So now that we know what the expected value and covariance
is, it's time to look at the most important distribution
of them all, at least in this course.
And that is the Gaussian distribution.
And as you will see, there is a clear connection
with the mean and covariance of a random variable.
So we write like this to denote that x
is a Gaussian random variable with mean mu and covariance Q.
And the pdf of x is then denoted like this, so p
of x where we use this notation here to denote the Gaussian
pdf as a function of x with the parameters mu and Q.
Note that there's a important difference with what
we write here, where we are saying that x is distributed
according to Gaussian distribution
with these parameters, mu and Q. But here we are referring
to the actual function as a function of x
with these parameters.
So by definition, the Gaussian pdf
can be expressed like this, where
we have here a constant term, which
is dependent on the covariance, times the exponential
to the power of a quadratic function of x.
We will have x minus its mean squared, which
is then normalized by or scaled by the covariance matrix
inverse.
If we plot this function here in the scalar case for a Gaussian
distribution with mean 0 and variance 1,
we get this classical bell-shaped curve,
where the peak is at the mean, which is 0 in this case,
and the spread around the mean is dependent on the variance.
So note that a Gaussian random variable is completely
determined by its mean and its covariance matrix.
So we do not need any other parameters to describe
a Gaussian distribution.
Later in this course, we will use this extensively
when we describe the results of our filters.
One of the nicer properties with Gaussian random variables
is what happens when we have a linear combination
of independent Gaussian random variables.
So let x and y be Gaussian random variables
with these means and covariances.
If we now construct a new random variable
z, which is then a linear combination of x and y
like this, so z is equal to A times
x plus B times y, where A and B are now deterministic matrices.
Then z will also be a Gaussian random variable, which mean
can be calculated like this.
So the mean of z is the expected value of Ax plus By.
Now, as we can always split the expectation of a sum
into its individual components, we get the expected value of Ax
plus the expected value of By.
And A and B are deterministic matrices,
we can move them outside of the expectations.
So we get A times the expected value
of x, which is mu x, plus B times the expected value of y,
which is mu y.
Now for the covariance, it's a bit more tricky.
But by definition, the covariance of z
is equal to the covariance of Ax plus By.
We just insert what z is, right?
Now, as x and y are independent, we
can divide this covariance of this sum
into the covariance of the different parts here
or the different terms in the sum.
Now, note that we cannot do this in general,
as we need to consider the cross-covariance terms,
which in this case is the cross-covariance of Ax,
By and the cross-covariance of By and Ax.
But as x and y are independent, these terms here are 0.
So we can ignore them here.
Now again, as A and B are deterministic,
we can move them outside of the covariance.
But instead of getting them just as a factor
that we got here when we calculated the mean,
we get them squared here.
And as we're dealing with matrices,
we need to be a bit careful about which order
we do the square.
So in this case, we get A times Qx, A transpose,
plus BQy, B transpose.
And this is a general rule for the covariance.
So if you have a covariance of deterministic matrices
times a random vector, the result
will be A times the covariance of the random vector
times A transpose.
Now, if you feel that I went through this a bit quickly,
I would highly recommend that you
try to derive this expression here yourself
using the definition of covariance
that we presented at the beginning of this lecture
and perhaps also brush up on rules related
to the expectation operator.
And I will think that you will find this well worth the effort
when we start to discuss the actual material of this course.
For your convenience, here is a summary of the basic statistics
result that we have presented in this set of primer
in statistics lectures.
I would encourage you to familiarize yourself
with these expressions and make sure that you
understand what they are.
You might also find this slide handy
when we go through the results about nonlinear
filtering and the rest of the lectures in this course.