So now we know what a discrete-time state space
model is.
In this lecture, we're going to look
into conditional independencies and dependencies that
are inherent in these models.
And perhaps most importantly, we will
see how these conditional independencies will
help us to factorize our filtering distributions,
such that we can express them using
just three types of models.
Our motion models, our measurement models,
and a prior.
As we discussed in the previous lecture,
we have two forms of our state space models.
We have one equation form, like this,
and we have one density form, like this.
When we presented the state space models
on this form, the equation form, we explicitly
mentioned that, we assumed that both the motion
noise, qk minus 1, and the measurement noise, rk,
which entered these models here, that they
were independent of all other noise vectors.
The corresponding assumption, when we have the density form,
would look like this.
So if we start by looking at the distribution of xk,
conditioned on all past states and all the past measurements.
So we look at all the states, from the prior to the state
at k minus 1, and all the measurements
from the first measurement, up to k minus 1.
We assume that we can write this distribution here
like this distribution here, where we only need to condition
on the past state at k minus 1.
What we're assuming here, is that if we know xk minus 1,
xk is conditionally independent of all the other states and all
the other measurements, except xk minus 1.
If we relate this to the independence assumption
that we have here, we see that if we know the previous state
xk minus 1, the only thing that we are uncertain about
is the motion noise, qk minus 1.
So we know xk minus 1, the only thing we are uncertain about
is qk minus 1, you know to solve this equation here.
But as qk minus 1 is independent of all other noise processes,
we can't get any information about it
from knowing the past states or the past measurements.
As such, they do not help us to describe the density of xk,
so we may just as well remove it from this expression here.
Now, if we look at the distribution of the measurement
yk, again given all the previous states up to the current time
and the past measurements, we assume
that we can simplify this as just a measurement model.
Again, what we are assuming here is
that, if we know the current state, xk, the measurement, yk,
is independent of all past states and the measurements.
This can also be seen from the structure of the measurement
model and this assumption here.
That if we know xk, the only thing that we are certain about
is rk.
And as we assume that rk is independent of all
the other vectors, we can't get any information about it
from knowing the past states and the observations.
A consequence of this is that for this to hold,
the state vector needs to summarize everything
we need to know about the system up to the current time.
If not, we cannot express these models on this form,
or on this form.
As such, in some cases we need to select our state vector
carefully in order for this to hold.
This usually means that we need to add more variables
in our state vector.
We should also note that xk and yk are stochastic processes.
And the assumption here implies that xk is
what's called a Markov process.
In fact, it's even a stronger statement,
as in order for xk to be Markov, we only
require that xk is conditionally independent on all
the past states, if we know xk minus 1.
Here we state that it's also conditionally
independent of all the past measurements as well.
A useful tool when thinking about conditional
independencies and dependencies is
what's called a Bayesian network, or what's also
called a belief network or Bayes net.
This is a probabilistic, graphical model
that uses a graph to illustrate how stochastic variables relate
to each other, or how they depend on each other.
There are many such graphical models.
But specifically, Bayesian networks
are directed acyclic graphs, where
each node is a stochastic variable,
and the vertex between two nodes, or stochastic variables,
indicate that there is a dependency
between the stochastic variables.
And with directed we mean that each vertex in the graph
has a specific direction.
And acyclic means that if we start in any node in the graph,
and only move in the direction of the vertices,
we cannot get back to the same node as we started in.
So there are no cycles in the graph.
The main purpose of these graphs is to describe a joint density
and how it can be factorized.
But it also illustrates conditional independencies.
And we're going to look a bit more into this.
So let us look at this from a small, toy example.
Where we want to reason about, if a vehicle in front of us,
we are in this vehicle here, and we see this vehicle here.
And want to reason about if this vehicle here in front
should take this exit here or not.
What we can observe is whether this vehicle here
is slowing down, or if the turn indicator is activated.
So for this problem we have three random variables.
We have take exit, slow down, and turn indicator.
In our Bayesian network, these are three nodes in our graph.
I will indicate our nodes by drawing circles around them.
We connect these nodes with directed vertices indicating
how they depend on each other.
So whether the turn indicator is active or not
is dependent on whether the vehicle intends
to take the exit or not.
We have a dependency between take exit and turn indicator.
Similarly, if the vehicle is taking the exit,
there is a greater probability that the vehicle
is slowing down in order to safely take that exit.
One way of viewing this model, and the direction
of the arrows, is in terms of causality.
If the vehicle intends to take the exit,
it causes the vehicle to slow down and or turn on the turn
indicator.
It also gives us information regarding
how one could go about generating
these random variables here.
If I were to do this, I would first
generate if the vehicle would take the exit or not,
and then use this when generating the other two.
As, clearly, it helps to know if the vehicle intends
to take the exit, or not, when generating
if it is also slowing down, or if it's activating the turn
indicator.
This is because, as we see from the graph,
there is a direct dependence for these two variables,
if the vehicle intends to take the exit or not.
All right, so this makes sense, right?
But does this mean that slow down
is independent of turn indicator?
Well, not really, right?
If we reason about it, it seems reasonable
that, if the turn indicator is active,
it's also more probable that the vehicle will slow down
in order to take the exit safely, and vice versa.
But what happens if we condition on the vehicle
will take the exit, that is we know
for certain that the vehicle will take the upcoming exit?
What happens then with the dependency between slowing
down and turn indicator?
Well, the reason why they are dependent
is that we are uncertain about whether the vehicle will
take the exit or not.
However if we conditioned on this,
we can be quite certain that the vehicle also
will slow down and safely take the exit.
And if the turn indicator is active or not,
that becomes more of a personal choice.
So conditioned on that the vehicle will take the exit,
slow down and turn indicator becomes
conditionally independent.
The general conclusion is that, if we're
conditioned on a parent, the general conclusion
is that if we condition on a parent node,
so take exit as a parent to slow down
and turn indicator because it is preceding them in this graph,
the child nodes become conditionally independent
on all the non-descendants.
So if we would add extra nodes here,
they would not be independent of those but all non descendants.
So turn indicator becomes independent of slow
down in this case.
We can also see this if we factorize
the joint probability of all these variables using
the product rule.
And then using this Bayesian network to see how
we can simplify the expression.
So if we denote take exit as the random variable E,
turn indicators I, and slow down as S,
we can write the joint probability
of all these variables as probability of S, I, and E.
And using the product rule, we know
that we can factorize this joint density like this.
So we know that we can always do this for any joint density.
We're just using the product rule here.
But if we now look at this expression
here and take a look on our Bayesian network,
we know that S is independent of the turn indicator,
I, if we condition on E. So in this expression here,
we know that we can remove I from this expression.
So this can be simplified using our Bayesian network
to this expression here.
Which is something a bit more simpler
than the general expression that we got here.
Because we could remove the dependence on I here,
so we'll get a simpler expression here.
So in general, if we can formulate a Bayesian network
for a problem, we can use that to see
how we can factorize our joint distribution into as
small pieces as possible.
So we have now introduced the concept of Bayesian networks,
at least in the form of an example.
What we want to do now is to use it
to illustrate the dependencies and independencies of our state
space models.
So what we see here is a Bayesian network illustration
of our state space model, where we
can divide the model into a hidden part and an observed
part.
The hidden variables, in this case,
is the state space variables xk minus 2,
xk minus 1, and xk and so forth.
And the observed variables are our measurements
or observations, yk minus 2, yk minus 1, and yk and so on.
Where, for example, yk minus 1 is an observation of our state
xk minus 1.
This Bayesian network here gives us
some intuition regarding the dependencies
between our variables.
It also illustrates the models that we have.
For example, we see that xk minus 1
is dependent on xk minus 2.
So if we know xk minus 2, we can generate xk minus 1
using our process model for example.
So this vertex here basically says that p of xk
minus 1, given xk minus 2.
We have this type of model in our network.
Similarly, as we mentioned earlier,
our observation yk minus 1 is dependent on the state
at time k minus 1.
And this dependency is described by the measurement model,
right.
As a consequence of this, we can also see that, for example,
yk minus 1 is conditionally independent
on all other variables if we know xk minus 1.
And similarly, if we know xk minus 1,
for example, the variables here, to the right,
are no longer dependent on these variables here.
Because they are non-descendants of these variables.
And everything that we need to know
is summarized in xk minus 1.
Before we use this model to factorize our distribution,
I would like to point out two things.
The first thing is that we do not
expect that you will become an expert in Bayesian networks
after this short introduction.
However we hope that it will help
you to understand and remember the dependencies
and independencies that we have in our state space models.
And we should also note that the Bayesian network here does not
introduce any new information, it only
illustrates the dependencies and independencies
that we already introduced in the first slide.
The second thing is that, although the Bayesian network
illustrates how we model our random variable,
we use, for example, xk to generate yk.
But when we do inference, information typically
flows in the opposite direction.
Where we observe yk to draw conclusions
regarding our state, xk.
It's just that it is often convenient to model it
the other way around.
To model yk conditioned on xk.
So now, let's use the Bayesian network
to simplify our factorization of the joint distribution over all
our variables.
So we have the joint distribution
where all our states from the prior to time k,
and all our observations from time 1 to time k.
We can always factorize this using the product rule.
So we can, for example, divide it into this density
here where we have our observations conditioned
on all our states, and then just all our states.
Now we can split this up even further
if we separate this density here into factors
over individual observations.
We have p of y1, given all the states, p of y2, given p of y1,
given all the states.
This is just using the product rule, right?
And so forth.
Up to p of yk, given all the previous measurements
and all the states.
Similarly, we can split the density over all our states
into individual densities of each individual state.
So we have our prior, p of x0.
Then the density of x1, given x0.
Then the density of x2 given x0 and x1.
And so forth, until we have p of xk,
given all the previous states.
So note that we have not made any assumptions yet,
we have only used the product rule
to factorize the joint density.
So we go from joint density into these factors using the product
rule.
And we can do this for any density.
And now we want to use our Bayesian network here
to simplify these factors.
If you start by looking at these conditional distributions
over our individual observations,
we see from our patient network that each measurement, here,
is conditionally independent of all other states
and measurements.
If we condition on its respective states.
So if we condition on xk minus 1, yk minus 1
becomes conditionally independent
of all of these other states.
Because these are non-descendants of yk minus 1.
So if we look at it here as y1 it's conditionally independent
of all other states, except x1, we can remove them from this.
So we have for the first one here.
And then here we have y2, conditioned
on y1 and all the other states.
And here we have x2, right, so y2 is conditionally
independent of all the other states here, except x2.
So it simplifies to this.
And so on until we get.
So it leaves us with a product of measurement models.
So instead of having this very complicated product
of densities, we have a simple product
of our measurement models.
And that is all.
It's much simpler than that original expression, right?
Similarly, if we look at this product
here, over the individual states,
we can remove all the past states in this product here.
So the prior we cannot simplify anymore.
And not distribution of x1, given x0 either.
However here we see that, if we condition on x1,
x0 is conditionally independent of x2,
so we can remove it from the expression.
And we can do this for all the rest
and we just get: So we can just simplify
this fairly complicated product here
as just a product of the prior and the individual motion
models.
So by using the structure of our state space model,
as illustrated by this Bayesian network,
we can factorize the joint distribution
of all these variables as a product of simple measurement
models, process models, or motion models, and the prior.
So we will use this in the next lecture
where we will drive the optimal filter.
And here is a self-assessment question
to check that you have understood the basic concepts
of a Bayesian network.