Now it's finally time that we put all these things together
and learn how to do filtering.
In this lecture, we will derive the equations
for the optimal filter, which are general equations
that we can use to solve any filtering problem that we
will encounter in this course.
We will show how we can calculate
our filtering densities efficiently
by making the filter updates recursively,
and we will illustrate the computed densities
using a simple example.
But before we start, we need to properly define
the filtering problem.
So remember our discrete time state space models
where we have a state vector xk and an observation yk.
So we described how the state evolves over time using a known
motion model like this and how our observations
relate to our state vector using a measurement model like this.
Further, we suppose that we have some prior distribution that
is known to us and that the state at time k
is conditionally independent on all the previous measurements
or past measurements and that the state at time k
is conditionally independent on all the past measurements
and the past states if we condition on xk minus 1.
All the past states here and all the past measurements
here does not include any more information about xk
than what the previous status does.
And this equality here is what's called a Markov property.
We also assume that the current measurement, yk,
is conditionally independent of all other states, x0
to k minus 1, and all the past measurements
if the condition on xk.
So we can remove all the past states
and all the past measurements in this expression
here because all the information should be summarized
in the current state.
So remember that a necessary condition for these
to hold true is that both the motion and measurement noise
processes need to be independent over time and with each other.
So in this setting, the objective in filtering
is to compute the so-called filtering density, which
is this posterior density of xk given observations up to
and including time k.
And typically we want to do this for k equal to 1,
2, 3, and so on.
So in principle, as we know Bayesian statistics,
we can also find this posterior density.
In a bit of a brute-force approach,
we can find this filtering density in two steps.
First, we can use Bayes' rule to find
the posterior density of the complete sequence of state
vectors--
so the collection of states from time 0 to time k.
And this posterior density we conditioned
on all the measurements up to time k.
If we use Bayes' rule, we can now flip these two such
that we get this factor here where the density is now
over the set of measurements, and we condition
on our state sequence.
And then we have time steps prior on our state sequence,
and we get this normalization factor here.
Note that we can regard this as a normalization factor
as we're interested in this as a function of our state sequence
and this factor here does not depend on that.
So we see that we can express this posterior density here
over the state sequence as a product of our measurement
models and our prior.
And these are models that we all know, so we can express this.
Now as a second step, to get the filtering density
we need to marginalize the state sequence posterior with respect
to all the past states.
That is the states that we are not
interested in at the moment.
That is we find a filtering density
by integrating our sequence posterior
over all the past states.
As we see here, we can use Bayes' rule in combination
with the law of total probability
to calculate the filtering posterior.
Although we, in theory, end up with the correct solution
following these two steps here, in practice
the complexity of the solution will
grow as the state sequence here will become larger and larger.
This has two implications.
For one, this density here will become more and more complex
and will involve the multiplication of more and more
factors here as k grows.
Second, the integration here will
be taken over a larger and larger space,
and the complexity of this integral
will become larger and larger.
As such, it will become harder and harder
to calculate this filtering density.
As we typically want to calculate this posterior
density at each time step k, we tend
to want the complexity to be roughly the same at each time
instance and especially not grow over time.
So the weakness with this approach
is that it grows with k.
Now is there a smarter way to calculate
the filtering density that does not have this weakness?
But of course there is!
The solution is that we calculate the filtering density
recursively where the general approach or methodology is
that we want to use that we have just calculated the posterior
density from the previous time instance,
and we want to use this together with our conditional
independence assumptions to calculate the new posterior
at the current time.
So here is an illustration that summarizes
the general methodology of the recursive filtering solution.
So we assume that we have computed the posterior density
from the previous time instance.
That is we have computed p of xk minus 1 given measurement
of 2 times k minus 1.
So we know this already.
The next step is to take this density, which summarizes what
we know about the state at time k minus 1,
and predict that in time such that it says something
about the state at the current time.
So we want to calculate this predicted density here,
and we do that with a prediction step
where we use our motion model.
So the motion model enters here.
So after the prediction, we get what is
called the predicted density--
so the density of the state at the current time
given measurements up to the previous time instance.
So this describes what we know about the current state given
all the past measurement.
Now we want to use this predicted density
with the current observation, yk,
to get the posterior filtering density.
In order to do that, we will make use of our measurement
model in an update step.
So the measurement model enters in the update step.
So once we have computed the posterior density,
we can compute an estimate of our current state.
We call that x hat k given measurements up to time k,
and we write that like this.
And we can start all over again, so making this our new prior.
So we exchange this for this, and then we make this again.
So we have a recursive solution starting from the posterior
density from the previous time instance.
We make a prediction, and then we make an update,
and we get a new posterior density.
So note that all the densities that we have computed here,
they all have the same dimensionality as the state.
So we have avoided that the computational complexity grows
with time, so making these things here
have roughly the same complexity each time we do it.
So now we seem to have something that is a bit more reasonable.
The only question now is how do you actually
calculate this predicted density and this posterior density
here?
We start by looking at the prediction step.
Here, we want the predicted density, so the density of xk
given all the past measurements, and we
want to calculate this from our posterior density,
so the density of xk minus 1 given
all the past measurements.
So in this step we make use of our knowledge regarding
our previous state, xk minus 1, that we
have obtained from our previous measurements
in order to predict xk, so the state at the current time.
That is we want to translate our old knowledge about our states
that is summarized in this posterior density
to describe the state at the current time using
this predicted density here.
As hinted previously, we want to use our motion model, p of xk
given xk minus 1, together with our posterior density
from the previous time instance in order
to compute the predicted density.
So a useful first step is to introduce the missing variable
here, which is the previous state, xk minus 1.
And we can do this by using the law of total probability
where we add the previous state and this expression here.
So we get p of xk and xk minus 1,
conditioned on all the past measurements.
And in order for the equality here to still hold true,
we need to integrate out over our added previous state.
So we need to integrate over xk minus 1.
Now if we look at this, we can see
that we can factorize this density here by splitting up
these two into two densities.
The first is over xk given xk minus 1
and all our past measurements, and then just over xk minus 1,
given all our past measurements.
And note that we now have the posterior
density from the previous time instance here, which we wanted.
However, we also have this strange-looking density here.
But if we look a bit more carefully at this,
I hope that you can recognize it from before
and remember that our current state is conditionally
independent on the measurements if we condition
on our previous state.
So this is the Markov property of our state sequence.
Now if we use this, we see that we
can remove the past measurements from this density
as they do not provide any information about xk when
we condition on xk minus 1.
And this is because xk minus 1 should summarize everything
that we need to know about the system up to that time.
By doing this, we see that this density here simply becomes
our motion model.
Now the final expression for the predicted density becomes--
so our motion model times our posterior
density from the previous time instance.
And then we integrate over our previous state.
And this equation here, it's called
a Chapman-Kolmogorov equation, and that
is what we use in the prediction step in a recursive filter.
So to summarize, in order to compute the predicted density,
we use the posterior density from the previous time instance
together with our motion model to solve the Chapman-Kolmogorov
equation to get this density.
So here is a self-assessment question
that you could answer by solving equations
on the previous slide, but here I would rather
like you to think about it from a conceptual point of view
and think about what would make more sense.
So now onto the measurement-update step
where we want to compute the posterior density,
so the density of xk given all the measurements up to time
k using this predicted density that we just calculated
in the prediction step.
So in principle, what we want to do in this step
is that we want to update our knowledge about xk using
the new information in yk.
So we go from this predicted density
where we don't include yk to this posterior density
where we include information from yk,
the current measurement.
To derive the updated posterior density,
we start by separating out the current measurement
from this measurement sequence here such that we get something
looking like this.
We do this just to make what will happen
in next step a bit more clear.
Now in order to get out the predicted density,
we can use Bayes' rule to switch places on xk and yk,
in this case.
So if we use Bayes' rule to switch xk and yk,
we get the following expression.
So we get the predicted density here,
which we wanted, and this density here
could be regarded as a constant as it does not
depend on our current state.
Now if we look at this factor here,
we can see that we can simplify this as a likelihood function
or measurement model as yk is conditionally
independent on all the past measurements
if we also condition on xk.
So we can remove this factor here from our density.
Again, this is due to that everything
that we need to know in order to describe
the current measurement should be summarized
in our current state.
So if we ignore the proportionality constant,
the updated density can be defined as proportional
to this expression here--
so proportional to the likelihood
times the predicted density.
So in the update step of a recursive filter,
we see our predicted density as our prior
that we multiply by our likelihood
to get our posterior density.
So now we have also derived an expression
for the measurement-update step in our recursive filter,
and we have expressed it in terms of our predicted density,
which we have calculated in the prediction step,
and our measurement model which we assume that we know.
We should note that this expression
here and the expression that we derived
for the predicted density are general expressions.
So these expressions here are general,
and they provide a recursive solution
to any filtering problem.
We will, in later parts of this course,
look at how we can solve these equations exactly when we have
the so-called linear and Gaussian models
and how we can find good approximations
if we have a nonlinear and non-Gaussian model.
To wrap things up, I thought we'd look at a simple example
to see what is happening in the different steps of the filter
recursion and how the resulting densities look like.
We will do this by considering a random walk in two dimensions
where we also get position observations.
That is we have a two-dimensional state vector,
xk, which has two components, x1 and x2,
and we can think of this as a 2D position of some object.
The motion of this object is using a motion model
like this where the current state is
equal to the state at the previous time
instance plus some noise, where the noise in this case
here is a zero-mean Gaussian with some covariance Q.
So here we can see a realization of a random walk
of this process model here where we can interpret this basically
as the state, the position of the object
is basically taking a step of random length and direction
at each time instance.
We are randomly walking around in this 2D environment,
and hence the name random walk.
And this is a fairly simple motion model
but nonetheless it's important and used in many situations.
So further, at each time instance
we observe the position of our object.
So yk is our state plus some measurement noise, rk.
And rk, our measurement noise, is, again, a zero-mean Gaussian
process with some covariance R. And in addition, we
have some Gaussian prior of our state
at time zero, which is 0 mean with some covariance P0.
So how does a prior, predicted density, likelihood,
and updated density look for the optimal filter
solution for this problem?
So that's what we're going to look at now.
If we look at this for some generic time k,
at the start of the recursion we have the posterior density
from the previous time instance.
So we have the density over xk minus 1.
This gives us the information that the object of interest
was most likely here somewhere at the previous time instance.
And now we want to use this information, together
with our motion model, to predict where it
would be at the current time.
So we want to calculate the predicted density of xk given
all the past measurements.
Note that as we are doing predictions into the future
and not adding any new information here,
we will become more uncertain, which
is illustrated that this density here is wider than we
had when we started here.
This is also logical considering a random walk motion
model which states that the object will
take a step of a random length and a random direction.
And as long as we haven't received
any information about which direction the object has moved,
we will surely be more uncertain after doing the prediction.
The next step is that we will make use of our measurement
update where we view our predicted density here.
So we have predicted density here as our prior
and our measurement model as our likelihood.
So in this case we get an observation
that an object is here somewhere if we are projecting down
the peak here onto the plane.
The likelihood of our state would look something like this.
So it says that it's most probably here somewhere,
but as we have measurement uncertainty,
we are also uncertain about where
the object is after receiving the measurement.
Now if we multiply our predicted density with our likelihood,
we have something that is proportional to our updated
posterior density.
We can see that, in this case, our measurement
is fairly informative so that the updated density is fairly
close to where the observation was,
which was here somewhere, right?
And we are definitely further away
from the predicted density, which we thought that object
was around here somewhere.
We should also note that uncertainty decreases
after the update as we have gotten
new information regarding where the object is
from the measurement.
So to summarize, we start off with our initial prior,
which is our posterior from the previous time instance.
We do a prediction step to calculate
our predicted density, which describes
our state at the current time using
all our past observations.
So while doing this, our uncertainty about the object
will increase as the data that we used is getting a bit older.
So we are only basing this on observations up
the time k minus 1 but still describing the state
at the current time.
So by performing the measurement update where we multiply
the predicted density by our likelihood of the state using
our observation at time k, we incorporate the new information
in the new observation to compute the posterior density.
That is, again, a bit more certain about
where the object is.
So this is basically what is happening
in the filter recursion.
In future lectures, we will look into more details surrounding
the mathematics around calculating these densities
here for different types of state space models and also how
we can find approximate solutions to the posterior
density when we cannot solve the prediction and update
the equations analytically.