Welcome to this section, where we will give an introduction
to Bayesian statistics.
Besides being one of my favorite subjects,
the theory of Bayesian statistics
also underline all nonlinear filtering
and sensor fusion methods that we will present in this course.
Although you can easily spend years studying
all the facets of it, our aim for this section
is to give you a basic understanding
of the concepts which Bayesian statistics is built upon.
In this first lecture, we will focus
on giving you more of an overview of the subject,
without going into too much details.
So what is Bayesian statistics?
Well, it's a statistical inference framework,
which means that we can use it to make decisions or draw
conclusions regarding some parameters of interest using
data where there is typically some inherent uncertainty
in the data.
A typical example is that the data is imperfect and noisy
and can thus not give us exact information regarding
what we are interested in.
Instead, we want to use Bayesian statistics to try
to extract as much good information as possible
from our noisy observations.
In many ways, Bayesian statistics
is a very flexible framework, which
can be used for many different types of decisions.
For example, the same basic theory and methods
can be used for estimation, classification, detection,
and model selection, and so forth.
The key characteristic being that, whatever problem that
we are facing, the unknown quantities
are described as random.
This could, for example, be the type of disease of a patient,
the transmitted message in a communication system,
the temperature in the cylinder in an engine,
or the intention of a driver in a traffic situation.
To make things a bit more concrete,
let's look at using Bayesian statistics
in a medical application.
Let's say that we want to analyze
the disease of a patient.
In this case, the quantity of interest
that we want to apply Bayesian statistics to try
to make a decision on is the disease of the patient.
Let's denote the variable that describes the disease as theta.
To help us make decisions regarding
the disease of the patient, we make some observations.
And we make these observations by collecting and analyzing
blood samples, taking the temperature of the patient,
collecting comments by the patients
on experienced symptoms and so on.
In many cases, no one of these alone
will give us the conclusive answer
to the disease of the patient.
But if we weigh them together, the picture
usually becomes a bit clearer.
And we can use Bayesian statistics to do this.
An important aspect of Bayesian statistics is that theta--
the disease of the patient, in this case--
is described as random.
So it's a random variable.
By doing this, we can calculate the probability distribution
of the disease of the patient based on the observations
that we have made.
For example, we can make statements
like, based on our observations, the patient has
disease x with 97% probability.
A possible concern that one can have
regarding the Bayesian way of viewing things
is whether it's actually valid to say
that the disease is random.
Surely the patient has gotten a disease and not
any random disease.
However, there are many advantages
with viewing the disease as random.
For example, in many situations, we
will not be able to determine with 100% certainty which
disease the patient has.
By then viewing the disease as random,
it allows us to also express our uncertainty
in which type of disease the patient has.
For example, here, perhaps it's 97% probability
that the patient has the flu, but with 3% probability
it's just a common cold.
When deciding on appropriate action,
it's surely beneficial to know with which certainty
a diagnosis can be reached.
And could you come up with any other advantages?
Let's look at another example where
it's common to use Bayesian statistics
and which we'll use as an inspiration for many
of our examples in this course.
And that is automotive examples.
In this case, we look at self-driving vehicles,
which rely on their ability to position surrounding
vehicles in order to safely navigate its surroundings
and not cause accidents.
So let's assume that we have a self-driving vehicle, which
is equipped with a bunch of sensors, that observes
the traffic situation in front.
The quantity of interest is then the relative position
and velocity of the other vehicles at the current time.
So we want to know the relative position and velocity
to all of these vehicles here.
To do this, we'll make use of noisy observations
from the sensors on the self-driving vehicle.
This could be wheel speed sensors, or inertial sensors,
such as accelerometers and gyros,
on our own vehicles to measure how we are moving.
But we also need observations that
give us information about the position of the other vehicles.
This could, for example, be radar detections,
which gives us the distance and angle
to objects, or Lidar point clouds, or camera images
and so on.
One aspect I would like to highlight with this application
is that, in Bayesian statistics, vehicle motions
are modeled stochastically.
That is, we describe likely movements of the vehicles using
stochastic models, which helps us rule out
unrealistic trajectories.
If we look at the scenario here in a Bayesian perspective,
we would say that it's likely that this vehicle here
moves something like this.
That is, it is following the road more or less.
And it's unlikely that it will make a sharp U-turn like this.
Now, one possible concern one could
have is whether vehicles' motions actually are random,
and this underlines the basic Bayesian assumptions.
For completeness, we should mention
that there are two main strategies to decision making,
using Bayesian statistics, which we'll focus on in this course,
and using frequentist statistics.
The main difference between these two
are mainly on a philosophical level,
but which also has consequences on the actual calculations that
are made and the models that are used.
So in frequentist statistics, the quantities of interest
are described as unknown and deterministic and not
unknown and stochastic or random as in Bayesian statistics.
As a consequence, in the medical example
that we discussed earlier, a frequentist
would not state that, given the observations,
the patient has a flu with 97% probability
and the common cold with the 3% probability.
But will rather say something like, based on observations,
the patient's most likely has the flu.
And the differences is that, for a Bayesian,
the answer is a probability distribution
of the disease based on our observations,
while for a frequentist, the answer is
the most likely disease based on our observations.
Let us look at another example and try
to highlight the difference between viewing
the quantity of interest as unknown but deterministic
compared to unknown and random.
Let's say that we wish to estimate
the height of the Eiffel Tower.
Is the height random or not?
Well, in a frequentist perspective,
the tower has a certain height and it's therefore not random.
That is, it has some fixed but unknown value.
Using the Bayesian perspective, we describe our uncertainties
in the height by viewing it as a random variable
with a certain probability distribution.
In a sense, describing the height as random
becomes a useful tool to incorporate prior information
that we have about the height of the Eiffel Tower
before we make any observations.
I encourage you to think about this yourself.
What do you think makes most sense and why?
If you're not fully convinced that the Bayesian perspective
makes sense, I hope that I will be able to convince you
during this course.
I should also mention that, in many cases,
the frequentist and the Bayesian would end up
with the same answer, but there are also many cases
where they would disagree.
We will now leave the frequentist perspective
and focus our attention again on Bayesian statistics
by giving you an overview of the Bayesian strategy.
So suppose we wish to estimate some quantity of interest-- we
call this theta, given measurements on theta
that we call y.
The key steps in Bayesian methods
is that we first model everything that we need.
In this case, we need two models.
The first model describes what we know about theta
before making any observations.
And we do this using what's called a prior, which is
this distribution p of theta.
In the example of the Eiffel Tower,
we would here say that we know that the height of the Eiffel
Tower is somewhere between 250 and 350 meters.
And we would describe this knowledge
using our prior distribution like this.
So this is some prior knowledge that we
have about the height of the tower
before we even make any measurements.
The second model that we need in this case
is a probabilistic model of how the measurements
y relate to theta.
And we do this using the probability
density of y condition on that we know theta.
Note that, as we are often interested in this
as a function of theta, and that this is not a probability
density over theta but over y, to make this clear
we call this the likelihood of theta.
The second step is to make a measurement update, where
we combine what we knew from before from this
prior with our measurements, which
is described by this density, which we also
called a likelihood, right?
We summarize our knowledge about theta
in what's called a posterior density, which
is the probability density of theta after we observed y.
So y is now known.
Our observation is now known.
And the final step is to make a decision regarding theta.
In the example of the Eiffel Tower,
we would like to make a point estimate of the height.
That is, we would like to decide on one value of the height
instead of having this distribution of the height.
In general, we do Bayesian decision
making by taking what we know about a parameter theta,
as described by this posterior density,
and combine that with a loss function
that describes what are important aspects
in our decision.
The goal is then to compute an optimal decision that
minimizes the average loss over possible values of theta,
as described by our posterior density.
In the Eiffel Tower example, we typically
would like to find an estimate that is either
the most probable height or the estimate which, on average,
if we do this multiple times with new measurements
every time, has the lowest error.
We call this the MAP and the MMSE estimates, respectively.
And we will look at the loss functions
for these in a later lecture.
So, in this course, we will mainly
focus on the second step.
But we'll also discuss how we derive our models
and look at standard ways of decision making.
We wrap things up with a self-assessment question
for you to think about.