In this video, we are going to introduce
one of the more important tools that
is needed to do Bayesian inference,
and that is Bayes' rule.
Additionally, we will show how we can apply it
in a simple toy example involving picking fruits
from an urn.
If you remember the three steps involved in a Bayesian method
that we discussed in the previous video,
this would relate to the second step--
the measurement update.
Here is our toy example, where we're
going to select a fruit from one of these urns.
We start by selecting from which urn we are
going to pick our fruit from--
either the blue urn or the red one--
and we do so with equal probability.
It's a 50% chance we'll pick the red one and a 50% chance
that we'll pick the blue one.
From whichever urn that we choose,
we pick a fruit without looking.
Simple enough, right?
The question that we would like to answer,
using Bayesian statistics, is that,
if we picked an orange, what is the probability that we
chose the red urn to pick from?
To answer this question, we should first
go through some Bayesian statistics.
Bayesian statistics is simple.
We only need two rules.
The first is called conditional probability,
or, the product rule.
It states that we can always decompose the joint probability
of two random variables as a product with two factors.
In this case, we have two random variables, y and theta.
The product rule then states that we can always
factorize this joint probability as the conditional probability
of y given theta, times the probability of theta.
Note that the order here does not matter,
and we can always factorize it in the other way around.
We can factorize it as the probability of theta given y,
times the probability of y.
The second rule is called the law of total probability,
or the sum rule, which states that we
can find the marginal distribution
of a random variable by summing the joint probability
over all possible outcomes of the random variable
that we're not interested in.
In this case here, we're interested in probability mass
function of a discrete random variable, y,
which you can find from the joint probability of y
and theta by summing this joint probability
over all possible values of theta.
This is also called marginalizing our theta,
as we are essentially removing the influence of theta
from the joint, to get a marginal distribution of just
y.
For continuous random variables, the summation
is exchanged with integration, but the concept
is all the same.
Bayes' rule, which we will be using extensively
in this course, is basically a consequence
of conditional probability.
Remember that conditional probability
allowed us to decompose the joint probability of y
and theta in two ways--
either as the probability of y given
theta, times the probability of theta, or the other way around.
As both of these express the same joint probability,
there must be an equal sign here.
If we consider this equality and divide both sides by p of y,
we basically get Bayes' rule.
Bayes' rule states that p of theta given y
can be written as p of y given theta, times p
of theta, divided by p of y.
Note that this gives us the ability
to switch conditional probabilities, in that we can
express the conditional probability of theta given
y in terms of the probability of y
given theta and some other factors here which are usually
fairly simple.
This is the main usage of Bayes' rule.
It allows us to express a relation of interest,
p of theta given y, so the probability of the quantity
of interest, theta, given our observation-- which, in our toy
example would be the probability that we have chosen
a particular urn, given that we observed
that we have picked an orange.
We can express this in terms of a relation that we know,
which is p of y given theta.
In our toy example, being the probability
of picking a certain fruit, given
that we know which urn we pick from,
we should also note that the factor in our denominator,
p of y, can be found using the law of total probability
like this.
Express it in terms of these factors here.
Let's use this to solve our toy example.
We let theta be the quantity of interest--
which in this case is the color of the urn that we picked
our fruit from--
where r indicates that we picked from a red run
and b that we picked from the blue.
Further, we let y be our observation, which in this case
is which fruit we picked--
o as an orange and a for an apple.
If we remember, the question is, if we
know that we picked an orange--
so, y equals to o--
what is the probability that we picked
the orange from the red urn--
which in this notation would mean that theta equals r.
If we express this mathematically,
we would like to calculate the conditional probability
that theta equals r, given that y equals o,
which we write like this.
Probability of theta equals r, given that y equals o.
We are not able to calculate this probability directly
from what we know, however, without making
any observations we know that there is a 50% chance
that we have chosen the red urn.
The probability of theta being r is equal to one half.
Also, if we know that we picked the fruit from the red urn,
we can calculate the probability of picking orange,
as we see that there are six oranges in the red urn and two
apples.
The probability of picking an orange from the red urn
would be 6/8, or 3/4.
Mathematically, we would write this as probability of y
being equal to orange, condition on we picked from the red urn,
and this is 3/4.
How can we use this to express the probability
that we're interested in?
Well, if we use Bayes' rule, we can reverse the conditioning
here so that we get a term where these two factors have switched
places, which is exactly what we have right here.
Let's try this out.
Using Bayes' rule, we get--
So, we see that we get this factor here,
which is the probability that we pick
an orange if we know that we choose from the red urn--
which we know to be 3/4--
and this factor, which is the probability
that we have chosen the red urn without making
any observations.
This is one half, and then we get this factor here,
which is a marginal probability of choosing an orange.
We know this one, we know this one--
how can we calculate this one?
We can use one of the rules that we
know, the law of total probability, which
states that the marginal p of y equal to orange--
the marginal probability that we pick an orange--
is the probability of picking orange from the red urn, which
is expressed by the joint probability,
plus the joint probability that we have picked
an orange from the blue urn.
Now we can calculate these using the product rule, which
means that we decompose these into two factors which
are similar to the decomposition here.
For the first, we get the probability
of picking an orange--
given that we're picking from the red urn, which is 3/4--
times the probability that we're picking from a red urn, which
is one half.
Similarly, for the second term, we
get the probability of picking an orange, given that we
are picking from the blue urn--
as in the blue urn, there are only one orange
and four fruits in total--
times the probability of picking the red urn, which is one half,
again.
If we sum this up we see that this becomes one half.
When you put it all together to calculate
the probability that we have chosen the red urn--
given that we observe that we pick an orange--
we see that this is the probability
of picking an orange from the red urn, which
is 3/4, times the probability that we are picking
from the blue urn, which is one half, divided
by the marginal probability that we are picking an orange,
which we have calculated using the law of total probability
and conditional probability, to be one half.
If we solve this, we see that these cancel out
and we get the probability to 3/4.
The probability that we picked a fruit from the red urn,
given that we picked an orange, is 3/4.
We use Bayes' rule to calculate the conditional probability
using terms that we could more easily calculate,
or express, using conditional probability and the law
of total probability.