In the previous videos, we learned
that Bayesian statistics can be used to solve
almost any decision problem.
We also learned how to summarize what we know in a posterior
distribution.
In this video, we will discuss how to make decisions.
So given that we have all these uncertainties,
how can we then make a decision?
And more specifically, we will discuss
how we can use the Bayesian framework to make
optimal decisions.
So let's discuss the Bayesian Decision Principle.
The question here is how can we use p of theta given y
to make decisions.
Examples of decision problems can
be how to control a self-driving vehicle, for example.
That is decide on appropriate acceleration, braking,
and steering input in order to safely and efficiently navigate
a current traffic situation.
It can also be how to invest money,
both if you're running a company or as a private person.
We can also look at selecting medicine to give to a patient
if you're a doctor, or what estimate to give a parameter
vector that could represent temperature or distance
or any other quantity of interest.
So the basic principle of Bayesian Decision Theory
is simple.
It can be summarized like this.
So we want to minimize the expected loss.
Or more specifically, we want to minimize
the posterior expected loss which is how this posterior
distribution comes to play.
An alternative and equivalent formulation
is to use what's called utility instead.
So since we can replace loss with utility and minimization
with maximization, so instead of minimizing expected loss,
we can maximize the expected utility.
So this is simple enough, right?
But there are some pieces missing here
that we haven't really discussed.
And that is what a loss function is.
We will do this in this example.
So suppose there is a student who
wants to decide whether to take a course or not.
In this example, let's suppose that we have some posterior
distribution of the quality of the course,
having spoken to other students who have taken the course,
for instance, and taking our prior knowledge about the topic
into account.
Based on this, we find that the probability
that a course is good is 0.3, that a course is
fair is also 0.3, and that the course is bad is 0.4.
So the students that also designed a loss
function saying that if he or she takes the course
and it's good, there is zero loss.
So this is a good thing.
If he or she takes a course and it's fair,
there is a loss of 5.
And if the course is bad, it's a loss of 30.
Similarly, there is a loss associated
with not taking the course if it's good, fair, or bad.
The question is then, according to this posterior distribution
regarding the quality of the course
and this loss function here, should he or she then
take the course or not.
From an optimal decision theoretic point of view,
the student should make the decision that has the lowest
expected posterior loss.
So the student should decide to take the course
if the expected loss of taking the course
is less than the expected loss of not taking the course,
and vice versa.
So the expected loss for a specific decision
is what you get if you multiply the posterior probability
with the corresponding loss.
So 0.3 times 0 and so forth.
And then we sum these up to get the posterior expected loss.
So let's look at the expected loss for taking the course.
So we have 0.3 times 0 if the course is good
plus 0.3 times 5 if the course is fair and 0.4 times 30
if the course is bad.
If we sum all of this up, we get an expected loss of 10.5
for taking the course.
Now if you look at the expected cost for not taking the course,
we have 0.3 times 20 plus 0.3 times 5 plus 0.4 times 0.
Now if we sum all these up, we get an expected loss of 7.5
for not taking the course.
So we have now computed the expected loss
for the two possible decisions.
If the students choose to attend the course,
then we get an expected loss of 10.5.
On the other hand, if the student
decides not to take the course, we
get expected loss that sums up to 7.5.
So the conclusion here is that the student should not
attend this course.
Now of course, this toy example has
nothing to do with this particular course
and that you should all probably still attend this course.
Now let us see if we can introduce some more
mathematical notation for this.
We often study loss functions instead of utility.
So we have a loss function C of theta
where theta is the quantity that we're interested in
and where a denotes the decision which
is dependent on the outcome of theta.
So in the example that we just studied,
theta was the quality of the course
and a was the decision if the student should take the course
or not.
Now in this course, the decision that we want to make
relates to choosing an estimate of theta.
So if theta is, for example, the distance to an object
that we're interested in, then our estimate
is the distance that minimizes our expected posterior loss.
So to emphasize that we're actually
making a decision on theta, we usually
denote our decision as theta-hat, which
is then our estimate of theta.
Now in this context, the optimal decision
can in mathematical terms be described like this.
So we would like to find a theta-hat that
minimizes the posterior expected loss, which we can express
like finding the argument a which
minimizes the posterior expected loss, like this.
You should note that we condition on data here.
So y is given and fixed.
But theta is random.
We have uncertainty regarding theta.
We should also note that in an estimation problem,
theta is continuous so the expectation can
be calculated like this.
Now here is a self-assessment question
about making an optimal Bayesian decision.
My final remark in this video is something which is actually
beyond the scope of what I hope for you
to learn in this course.
But I'm including it since I think that some of you
might find it interesting.
Also, we have touched upon most of this previously
here and there.
So it might be good with a bit of a summary.
So like I said, there are two main frameworks
for making decisions.
It's the Bayesian framework and the Frequentist framework.
So in the Bayesian framework, uncertainties
in the parameter of interest theta
are described stochastically which
means that theta is modeled as random,
whereas in the Frequentist setting,
theta is fixed and unknown and thus theta is deterministic.
Now a very common example of an estimator in the Frequentist
framework is what's called a maximum likelihood
estimator, where the estimate is simply the value of theta that
maximizes the likelihood after observing the data y.
If you compare that to the Bayesian framework,
the corresponding estimator is the maximum
a posteriori estimator, which finds the theta that maximizes
the posterior distribution, which
is the product of the prior times the likelihood
after observing the data y.
So lastly, when it comes to optimality in the Bayesian
framework, we make decisions conditioned on the observation
y and take the expected value over the parameter theta.
In the Frequentist setting, on the other hand,
theta is deterministic.
So there is no way we can average over theta.
Instead we study performance by averaging over
y for fixed thetas.
What we're saying here is that our estimator
should be good on average for many different data.
While over here, we are conditioned
on a specific set of data y.
So there is quite a difference in the optimality criterion
for the two frameworks.
We should also note the following things.
Most Bayesians also study Frequentist performance.
So people who tend to use Bayesian framework
may also be interested in evaluating their estimators
in this sense here, where we fix the parameters
and study how it performs on average over many sets of data.
Also, there are many problems where Frequentists
agree that the parameters may be random in some situations.
For example, in optimal filtering,
which we will look at in this course,
most people agree that the parameters are actually
random and not deterministic.
So this could be, for example, the motion of vehicles
that we discussed earlier.