In the previous video, we learned
about the Bayesian decision principle,
which is to try to minimize the posterior expected loss,
or cost.
In this video, we will introduce two commonly used loss
functions for estimation problems.
We will then use these to derive the minimum mean square error
estimator, the MMSE estimator, as well
as the maximum a posteriori estimator, also known
as the MAP estimator.
In the Bayesian decision theory, there
are three important components--
the likelihood, the prior, and a cost function or a loss
function.
Using the first two, the likelihood and the prior,
we can compute the posterior distribution, like this.
And given the posterior distribution,
we can make decisions by minimizing the posterior
expected loss, like this.
So this summarizes the basic strategy
in Bayesian decision theory.
The most commonly used loss function in estimation theory
is the quadratic loss, which will
lead to the popular estimator, the minimum mean squared error
estimator, or MMSE estimator.
So suppose that we have an estimation
problem where we want to estimate a vector theta, which
is an Rn.
So as we said, a very common loss function in this setting
is the quadratic loss.
And the quadratic loss, we can express like this.
So we have a loss function, C of theta and a, which
is equal to this L2-norm of theta minus a squared.
Now this can be viewed as the square error
between the actual theta and our decision a.
Now, as theta is a column vector,
we can write this norm here as theta minus a transposed.
Now this is a row vector, due to the transpose,
times theta minus a, again.
And now this is a column vector, right?
So this product here becomes a scalar,
which it's supposed to be because this is a cost
function.
Now, just for illustration purposes,
let's assume that theta and a are scalars.
If we try to draw this cost function here
as a function of a for a fixed value of theta,
it would look something like this.
So let's assume that we have a theta here.
So we will have 0 loss of theta, and then the loss
will grow quite radically as a moves away from theta.
Now the interpretation of this is
that it's OK to make a small error,
as long as it's not too big.
So if a goes away too much from theta,
our loss will increase rapidly.
So before we derive the optimal estimator using this loss
function here, we should introduce some notation.
First, we'll let the theta bar be the expected value of theta
given y.
And second, we'll let P be the covariance matrix
of theta given y.
So there's a posterior covariance of theta
after observing y.
And it's, by definition, expressed like this.
Now, in order to derive the optimal estimator of theta,
it's useful to try to simplify the function that we're
trying to minimize.
So recall that we're interested in minimizing the posterior
expected loss, which is expected value of our cost
function conditioned on y.
Now, in this case, our loss function is this, right?
So if we insert this into our expression, we get--
theta minus a transpose, theta minus a.
Now, a useful strategy to find optimal a
is to simply take the gradient of this expression
here, with respect to a, and then set it to 0
and solve for a.
Although this is a perfectly fine strategy and something
that you might want to try yourself,
I personally prefer a different type of trick
in order to come up with a optimal solution.
We might call this trick, "To add an intelligent 0."
Now, this is just a trick that simplifies the calculations.
In this case here, we will add and subtract theta bar
in both of these terms here.
So we'll get something like this.
And I argue that this will simplify our derivation.
So I'm simply taking this here, and then I'm
adding and subtracting theta bar in each term here.
So what happens now is that this part here
is a 0 mean random variable.
And this part here is just deterministic value.
There's nothing random about this part.
As theta bar is just a vector, and a is another vector.
So this is deterministic.
That is, we have a 0 mean vector,
plus some deterministic vector, and then the transpose,
and then the product do the same thing.
What happens now is that we multiply these things together.
We will get one term, which is the 0
mean random vector squared.
Now, note that this term here does not depend on a.
So from a minimization point of view,
this term does not really matter.
Anyway, we can see that it's almost the same thing
as the posterior covariance here,
but the transpose is in a different place.
So while this is a matrix, this will become a scalar.
If we take a trace of it, it is possible to prove
that we can still write this in terms of P,
if we take the trace of it.
So this term here can be simplified to the trace of P.
Now this is not important, but I mention it here
for completeness.
The next term would be, for instance, theta minus theta bar
times theta bar minus a, which becomes this term here.
Now this is where it becomes interesting
because this is where the trick that we have done pays off.
Since the second part here is deterministic,
we can leave it outside the expected value here.
And since the expected value of theta is theta bar,
this is simply 0.
The expected value of this is 0.
So we get 0 times this, which is also 0.
So this term will disappear.
Now we get a similar term when we multiply this
with this, which is also 0.
So we'll get another 0 here.
So the first three terms here does not actually depend on a.
However, the fourth term does, which is this times this.
But it's actually deterministic, which
means that taking the expected value
is trivial, as nothing happens.
So we get just these two multiply with each other.
So theta hat minus a, transpose, theta hat minus a.
Now, the posterior expected loss is the trace
of P plus this term here.
Now this term does not depend on a, but this term does.
As we would like to minimize with respect to a,
it's fairly easy to see that we can do this
by setting a equal to theta bar, which would make this 0.
So 0 times 0, which is 0.
And that's a best loss that we can have in this case.
It's also easy to show that this is a unique minimum.
So to conclude, our optimal estimator, theta hat,
which we get by finding the argument a
that minimize the expected posterior loss, so
minimum a of the posterior expected loss.
And find that this is the posterior mean
of theta, which is theta bar.
Now this estimator is called the minimum mean square error
estimator--
now minimum, as we're minimizing something,
mean because we take the posterior mean, and squared
error because we had the quadratic loss of the error
between theta and our estimate.
Usually we denote this estimator as theta hat MMSE.
So choosing the posterior mean as our estimate would make sure
that we on average has as low a squared error as possible.
So that's what the minimum mean squared error estimator does.
Another important type of loss function
that's used in the estimation problems
is the so-called 0-1 loss, which we are considering here.
Again, the setting is an estimation problem
where the column vector theta is in Rn.
Our 0-1 loss function can then be described like this.
So C of theta and a is minus the Dirac delta
function of theta minus a.
Now the name comes from the discrete case
whether we get a loss of minus 1 when a is equal to theta,
and 0 for all other values.
An interpretation of this is that we only
care about picking the exact correct value of theta,
and all other values are equally bad.
So again, if we try to illustrate
this for the continuous scalar case
where the 0-1 loss function is not really
a proper 0-1 function.
But the interpretation is the same.
So if we have a fixed theta here, for example,
our loss as a function of a is 0 for all values not
equal to theta.
So we have 0 for all values not equal to theta.
Then, on the other hand, we get a minus infinity loss
when a is equal to theta.
So we have a Dirac delta spike here.
So this means that it's infinitely good
to set a equal to the true value of theta.
And note that if theta is different from a,
the loss is 0.
And independently on how big the difference is, it's still 0.
So we're basically saying here that we only really
care about guessing the correct value.
If it's incorrect, it's equally bad if it's just a bit off
or if it's really far off.
To get the optimal estimator, we can
start by looking at the posterior expected loss.
So the posterior expected loss is defined like this.
So if we replace this with our loss function,
we get this expression here, where
we get the expected value of minus delta of theta
minus a, condition on that we know y.
Now if we use a definition of the expected value on this,
it equates to this integral here where
we'll have minus the integral of our posterior distribution,
p of theta given y times our delta function of theta
minus a.
And then we integrate over theta.
Now, you might recall that as the delta function
is only non-zero, if theta is equal to a.
There is a rule that says that if you integrate over
a delta function like this, the result is the function here
evaluated at the value where the delta function is non-zero.
So what we simply get from this integral here is minus
the posterior distribution of theta given y, evaluated
at theta equal to a.
So the optimal estimator theta hat
is then argument a, which minimizes the posterior
distribution if theta is equal to a.
Now there's a minus sign here, so we
can replace minimization with maximization
and removing the minus sign.
So we get this, since it's the same thing
to minimize minus something as to maximize something.
Since we're merely evaluating this where theta is equal to a,
we can replace theta with a here.
And we get this final result here,
that the optimal estimator with respect to the 0-1 loss
is what we get when we find the theta that maximizes
the posterior distribution.
Now this estimator here is called
the maximum a posteriori estimator and often denoted,
theta hat MAP, like this.
We have now derived the two most famous Bayesian estimators,
namely the MMSE estimator and the MAP estimator.
Now here is a self-assessment question on this topic.