So now we get back to the interpretation and intuition
of the different components in the Kalman filter.
There is the Kalman gain, the innovation, and its covariance.
A key to be able to do this is to understand this density--
the density of the predicted measurement given observations
up to the previous time instance k minus 1, which we can show
is a Gaussian distribution like this--
where the mean is Hk, the measurement model matrix,
times the predicted mean of the state and Sk is its covariance.
It's easy to see that this product here is the mean using
the observation model.
So the observation model for our linear and Gaussian models
is just yk equals to Hk times xK plus some measurement noise r.
By taking the expected value of this conditioned
on the previous observations--
so the expected value of yk conditioned
on previous measurements--
if we exchanged yk using this expression here,
we simply get--
which by definition is simply--
as rk here is 0 mean.
Now, we see that the conditional expected value is
by definition precisely this.
So how can we interpret this?
Well, we see that the expected value of our observation,
given our previous observations, are just this Hk times
r, predicted mean of the state.
So this is what we expect the observation to be given all
our previous observation.
We can also show that the covariance of yk here is Sk
So Sk describes our uncertainty in this.
Now, if we look at the innovation,
vk we see that it's equal to the current observation yk
where we remove what we expect the measurement should be based
on our previous knowledge.
As such, vk captures the new information in yk
which we were not able to predict
using our old information.
And, finally, when we calculate the updated mean like this,
the Kalman gain is the factor which
will determine how much we should
trust the innovation over our old information
in the predicted mean.
One can imagine, for example, that if our observations are
very noisy, we would like the Kalman gain to be very small--
close to 0-- such that we do not trust these measurements
so much.
So this factor here should be close to 0,
such our posterior mean is more based on our predicted mean.
We end with a self-assessment question
where I would like you to think about what
are reasonable values for the Kalman gain
in some specific scenarios.