So in the previous lecture, we presented a solution
to the filtering equations for linear and Gaussian models.
For these models, both the predicted
and the posterior density is Gaussian.
And the mean and covariance of these
are given by the Kalman filter equations.
Although we gave some hints in the previous lecture
for why the Kalman filter equations actually make sense,
in this lecture, we will more formally derive them,
and we will do so from a Bayesian perspective.
Before we start,
However, we need to define some prerequisites
and some notation.
So foremost, we assume that we have a linear and Gaussian
model.
So the state at the current type is
equal to the state at the previous time instance,
times this transition matrix, A k minus 1.
To account for added uncertainty in the predicted state,
we also have this additive noise process, q,
which is soon to be Gaussian with zero mean and covariance q
k minus 1.
The observation yk is similarly describe
as a linear function of the state, xk,
multiplied by this measurement model matrix, Hk.
And again, we have this additive noise process,
r, which we can assume to be Gaussian with zero mean
and covariance Rk In this case.
Additionally, we also need to assume that the prior state x
naught is also Gaussian, with some mean and some covariance.
We should also note that an equivalent
way of expressing these models here
is to express them on their density form
like this, where the process or motion model is defined
as a density over xk, where we know
the state at the previous time instance, xk minus 1.
And the measurement model or likelihood
is defined as a density over the observation yk
if we condition on the current state xk.
I would encourage you to make sure that you understand the
that these two express exactly the same thing, just
in two different ways.
So the objective of this lecture is
to use these models and the assumptions
that we presented here to derive analytical expressions
for the predicted density.
That is the density over xk given measurements up
to time k minus 1.
And for the posterior density, which
is then the density over xk, but now we also
condition on the measurement at the current time, k.
So there are many ways to derive the Kalman filter expressions.
One possible way is to derive the Kalman filter equations
from the filtering equations.
To do this, we simply plug in the Gaussian densities
that we presented in the previous slide
into these equations, and then try to solve them.
So for example, we need to calculate this integral here
and we need to solve this product here.
Although it's completely possible to do so,
unfortunately this involves various matrix manipulations,
and it's rather tedious.
So what we're going to present here
is a more standard derivation, where we instead
make use of well-known, or at least
well-known for statisticians, results regarding
Gaussian distributions.
Additionally, we hope that this will give you
some better understanding for what's happening in the Kalman
filter and help you understand a bit better
the non-linear filters that are based on the Kalman filter
that we will learn later on in this course.
Let's start with the prediction step.
So the objective here is to compute the predicted density.
And to do so, we use two assumptions.
First, we assume that the posterior density
from the previous time instance-- so the density
over xk minus 1, given measurements up to k minus 1,
is a Gaussian density with this mean and this covariance.
So remember that for our linear Gaussian models
all our filter densities are Gaussian.
And as a Kalman filter is a recursive filter,
this is a relevant assumption to make.
Secondly, we assume that we have a linear and Gaussian process
model like this that we presented
in the previous slide.
With this in mind, what we want to do
is use these assumptions to calculate the mean
and covariance of this density.
We will base our derivation on the well-known result
that if we have two independent Gaussian random variables--
let's call them z 1 and z 2 in this case.
A linear combination of these two variables
is then also Gaussian random variable, where
the mean is just a linear combination
of the mean of the these variables and the covariance
can be calculated like this, from the covariance
of the individual Gaussian random variables.
We can easily derive these expressions
by using fundamental rules for the expectation and covariance
operator that we have learned in the beginning of the course.
So as xk minus 1 and qk minus 1 are
independent Gaussian random variables,
we can use this result directly on our motion model
to get the predicted density.
So we want to calculate our predicted density, P of xk,
given measurements up to k minus 1,
which equals a Gaussian density of xk where the mean is given
by the expected value of xk, as described by this process
model, where we condition on observations up
to time k minus 1.
So we have ak minus 1 times the expected value
of xk minus 1, given measurements up to k minus 1,
which is exactly this mean here.
And then the expected value of qk minus 1 is just zero.
So it's zero mean.
So we get nothing else.
For the covariance, we again use this expression here.
So the covariance of xk minus 1, which is this covariance here,
is then multiplied by the transition
matrix on both sides.
We have Ak minus 1 times Pk minus 1, given k
minus 1 Ak minus 1 transpose, according to this formula here.
And then we need to add the covariance for our process
noise, qk minus 1.
So that's qk minus 1.
To map this to the notation that we have,
we call this mean, x hat k given k minus 1,
and we interpret this as the estimate of x at time k,
given observations up to k minus 1.
And similarly, for the covariance
we call this Pk given k minus 1, which
is the covariance of xk conditioned on measurements
up to k minus 1.
And we see that what we calculate here
is exactly what we calculate in the prediction
step of the Kalman filter.
So we have now derived the prediction step
in a Kalman filter.
Before we tackle the update step in the Kalman filter,
we need to understand an important lemma
for conditional distributions of Gaussian random variables.
And it goes like this.
So if x and y or two Gaussian random variables
with a joint probability density function like this--
so we concatenate x and y into single vector.
And that vector then is Gaussian distributed
with mean mu x and mu y, which is simply
the expected value of x.
And mu y is simply the expected value of y.
And that covariance matrix of this joint vector
here has this structure, where P of xx is the covariance of x.
And Pyy is then the covariance of y.
And Pxy is then the cross covariance of x and y.
We denote this as the covariance of x comma y.
And where Pyx is simply the cross covariance between y
and x, which is simply Pxy transpose,
as a covariance matrix needs to be symmetric.
So these need to be the transpose of each other.
And this cross covariance is then
related to how x and y are correlated
to each other or dependent on each other.
One should note that this structure here is general
and that we haven't made any other assumptions than that x
and y are jointly Gaussian.
So given that two variables are jointly Gaussian,
we can always structure its mean and covariance in this matter.
So based on this, the lemma states
that the conditional distribution of x given
y, for example, is then also Gaussian, where the mean is
given by the mean of x.
But we slightly shift it compared to the prior mean
of x, by this term here.
We further see that this term here
depends on the distance between the actual y
and what we expect y to be.
And that we wait this distance by a ratio
that it's dependent on how correlated x and y are,
divided by how much uncertainty we have in y.
As a sanity check, we can see that if Pxy is 0--
so x and y are uncorrelated.
We see that this term disappears and the mean
is simply the same as before.
So if we observed y and they are uncorrelated,
it doesn't change the mean of x, which is to be expected, right?
For the conditional covariance on the other hand,
again, we take the prior covariance of x, Pxx,
and then we reduce it by this factor here.
And here we can make two observations.
First, as with the conditional mean
if x and y are uncorrelated, so Pxy is zero.
This term again disappears and the covariance
of the conditional density is the same
as the covariance for x.
So observing y, and x and y are uncorrelated,
doesn't change the covariance of x.
It doesn't give us any information on x.
Second, if on the other hand x and y are correlated,
the covariance of x, if we conditional y,
will always be less than the covariance of x because we
reduce it by this factor here, and this factor here
is always positive.
And this also makes sense, right?
If they are correlated, after observing y,
we should be less uncertain about x than before we
made observation.
So in sum, the lemma states that if we have two jointly Gaussian
random variables, the conditional density is also
Gaussian with the mean and the covariance expressed like this.
Perhaps you can already now see some patterns here
for how we can use this lemma to prove the update
step in the Kalman filter.
But let's look at this in some more detail.
So when we do the update step in the Kalman filter,
we assume that we have already made the prediction
step that we showed earlier.
That is, we have computed the moments
of the predicted density of xk given observations up
to k minus 1.
And we denote these moments as this.
Additionally, we observe a measurement y
at time k, which is related to the state at time k
through this linear measurement model.
So here we have two Gaussian random variables.
And in order to see that they are jointly Gaussian,
it is convenient that we use the measurement model
and rewrite it to express the joint random variable x comma
y.
So we have this joint variable, xk yk,
which we want to express as something times xk
plus something times rk.
So we want to write it on this form here.
And in order for this to hold true,
we see that we need to have the identity matrix here
and we need to have a 0 here.
And this needs to be Hk.
And this needs to be the identity matrix.
So now we see that this equations holds true.
So xk is equal to xk plus 0 times rk.
And yk is equal to Hk xk plus rk, which is what we see here.
So now that we have written it on this form,
it actually follows directly that we
can write the joint distribution of xk yk
condition on all the measurements up to k minus 1
as this Gaussian density.
And it's perhaps useful to map this back
to the notation that was used in lemma on the previous slide.
So we have the expected value of x here.
So this was-- we call this mu x.
And this is then mu y.
This we called Pxx.
And this whole expression here, we call that Pyy.
And this was then the cross covariance between x and y.
And this here was then the cross covariance between y
and x, which is actually equal to the cross covariance
between x and y transposed.
Now if we use the lemma on conditional Gaussian densities,
we can express the posterior density
as this Gaussian density where the posterior mean, x hat k
given k, is equal to--
so if you use the lemma on the previous slide,
we see that we can form this as mu x plus Pxy times Pyy
inverse times y minus mu y.
So simply using the lemma on the previous slide,
we see that we can formulate the posterior mean
as this expression here.
And if we now identify what these
are from what we see here, we see
that this is equal to x hat k given minus 1
plus Pxy, this expression here, pk given k minus 1
and Hk transpose.
And then Pyy is this expression here.
Remember from the previous lecture,
we actually call this Sk as the innovation covariance.
So to simplify things, we will call it Sk in this equation.
So we have Sk inverse times y is yk in this case
minus the expected value of yk given observations
up to k minus 1, which is given here.
Hk times x hat k given k minus 1.
So if we look at this, we can see that this here--
this difference here is what we call the innovation
in the previous lecture.
And this factor here in front of it
is what we call the Kalman gain.
So this is actually equal to call Kalman gain
times the innovation.
And this is exactly how the updated mean is calculated
in the Kalman filter.
So how about the posterior covariance?
So again, if we use the lemma, we
see that our posterior covariance
can be written as Pxx minus cross-covariance x and y
times Pyy inverse times Pyx.
And Pyx, we see that this is just a transpose of Pxy.
So we exchange it like this.
So if we identify what things are here-- so Pxx
is just a predicted covariance.
And then, Pxy is this expression here.
And Pyy is just Sk, so Sk inverse.
And then Pxy transpose is just this expression here,
but transposed.
So now, if we introduce a small little trick saying that Sk
times Sk inverse--
so this product here is simply the identity matrix.
So we can insert this into our equation
here without changing anything.
So if we rewrite this as--
and then insert this identity matrix here
in the middle, which we can take the transpose of,
as it's a symmetric matrix.
We get the following expression.
And if we look at this, we can see that this factor here
is actually the Kalman gain.
And this factor here is simply the Kalman gain transposed.
So with this, we have that the updated covariance matrix
is simply the predicted covariance
minus the Kalman gain times the innovation
covariance times the Kalman gain transpose, which
is also exactly how we presented it in the previous lecture.
So now we have also derived the update step
of the Kalman filter.
We have now derived a Kalman filter
using some well-known results regarding Gaussian densities.
And you might wonder, why is this important?
Well, from my perspective, I think
it's important from at least two aspects.
First, being able to derive the Kalman filter
offers some intuition into what the Kalman filter actually
does.
And secondly, by being able to derive the Kalman filter,
we can figure out how we need to adapt equations
if the underlying assumptions changes slightly.
This could, for example, be if we no longer
have zero mean process and measurement noise,
how do we then need to adapt these equations in order to fit
this slightly different model?
We end this lecture with a self-assessment question
where you can try out your intuition regarding correlation
and the distribution of random variables.