In this set of lectures, our aim is
to give the background needed to define and understand
the formulation of the optimal filtering problem
and how can you solve it in an efficient manner using
knowledge of Bayesian statistics.
That is, we will define and discuss the underlying modeling
assumptions we will use a tool called
Bayesian networks to illustrate how these assumptions affect
the dependencies and independencies
of our stochastic variables, and how
we can use this to make convenient simplifications
of our problems.
Lastly, we will show how we can use all this
to calculate the posterior density for a fairly
general problem family.
To start off however, I thought we'd
put it all in a bit of context.
What do we mean by filtering, and how does it
connect to the related estimation problems smoothing
and prediction?
So what is filtering?
Well, filtering is about recursively,
which usually means that each time
instance, estimating parameters of interest
based on measurements.
And these measurements can come from one sensor
or multiple sensors.
If they come from multiple sensors,
we usually call it fusion or sensor fusion.
But in theory, it's basically all the same.
And in this course, we will not focus so much
on whether our measurements come from one or multiple sensors.
If we know how to do it for one sensor, adding another sensor
is, in many cases, trivial.
To help us discuss the problem, we
need to introduce some notation.
So basically, throughout the course,
we will let xk indexed by some time index k,
be a vector that contains the parameters of interest.
And yk contain the measurements at time k.
As sensors tend to deliver data at discrete times
with fixed sample interval, time in this k typically,
refers to one such interval, and does it
at a discrete time index.
So using this notation, the filtering objective is
to compute the posterior density of our state xk,
using what we denote as y 1 to k where y 1 to k
is a vector containing all the data up to time k.
And as we discussed earlier, if we can compute this,
and we can for example, compute and the mmse estimate
or the map estimate of xk using this posterior density.
To make things a bit more concrete,
let us look at some filtering of fusion
problems in modern automotive applications.
So modern vehicles today are equipped
with several onboard sensors.
And this could be RADAR, LIDAR, or camera, for example.
We want to use noisy observations from these sensors
to estimate a more refined view of the current traffic
situation.
And so driver assistance systems in the vehicle
then uses this refined view to assess
if there is any dangerous situation that we need
to warn the driver of, or automatically intervene
in order to avoid a situation altogether,
or to mitigate its consequences.
For a self-driving vehicle on the other hand,
this is the basic information that is uses in order
to plan a safe and comfortable path that the control
algorithms in a car can then follow.
Let us look at this example here or illustration
here, where we have a host vehicle that is equipped
with a RADAR and a camera.
The RADAR will give us range, angle,
and range rate to objects reflecting the RADAR signal.
For example, this could be other vehicles in here,
but could also be the metallic guardrail here.
The camera on the other hand, can detect and classify
vehicles, but can also detect the lane markings on the road,
for example.
The information from these sensors
is then used to estimate for example,
the current relative position of velocity of other vehicles.
For example, we want to estimate where these vehicles are
and where it's heading.
And we can call this our state vector x1k for that vehicle.
And then we'll have another state vector
for this car called x2k.
And then for this car we call that x3k.
What we also want to do is we want
to estimate the current relative position and heading
and shape of the current lane.
Want to describe the geometry of our current lane like this.
We call this lk.
And this is crucial information if we
need to plan a path that keeps the vehicle in its own lane,
for example.
Similarly, we can use RADAR reflections from the guardrail
here to estimate relative position, heading,
and shape of the guardrail as well.
One can think of many more things
that we possibly would like to know but in order for them
to be classified as a filtering problem,
it should be related to estimating the current value
using data up to the current time.
We want to use as much data as possible
without introducing any lag.
So filtering is, of course, not only used
within the automotive applications.
One of the first applications was
related to finding the position and velocity of airplanes
and ships for military purposes, which is still an active area
today.
Within control of physical systems,
it is common to use filtering techniques to estimate
interior states of the system in order to better control it.
If we, for example, look at engine control,
this could be estimating the angle
of the crankshaft or the pressure in the piston in order
to control the fuel injection.
It is also quite common that you use filtering techniques
to estimate things that you are not able to measure directly.
And there are many such examples in the engine
where it's hard to place sensors everywhere.
But you can observe other things, which
relate to things that you are interested in,
and hence, estimate it using those observations
and using the techniques you will learn in this course.
You can also use filtering to assess the state in many others
types of systems such as biological and economical,
for example.
This could, for example, include estimating
the diffusion constant of a dissolvent and the solvent,
or the spread of a disease or the price of a commodity.
There are two problems that are related to filtering,
and that is was called smoothing and prediction.
The objective of all of these is to compute a probability
density function of state xk, but they
differ in how much data we condition on.
So let us assume that we have a positive integer that
is greater than 0.
In the smoothing problem, we want
to compute the distribution of xk
using measurements from 1 to k plus n.
That is, we want to use future data at times k to k plus n
to estimate a state a time k.
In the prediction case, it's rather the opposite.
Instead we want to compute the distribution of our state xk
using data from 1 to k minus n, that
is, we are trying to make predictions of the state using
all the data.
The relation between prediction filtering and smoothing
can be seen in this figure here.
In all the cases, we're interested in knowing the state
at time k.
We have not yet received so many measurements.
We have just received measurements up to k minus n,
but would anyway like to say something
about the state at the future time k.
When it comes to filtering, however, we
have received all the measurements up to time k,
and we want to use all these measurements to estimate
the current state.
And lastly, smoothing we have received more measurements.
So we have received measurements up to time k plus n.
And we want to use all of these observations
to also improve our knowledge about the state at time k.
So let us look at some examples of prediction and smoothing.
Let us first look at examples where
we use smoothing in automotive applications.
Many autonomous vehicles use detailed maps
to position themselves and to navigate.
These maps typically include detailed geometry of the lanes
and intersections, as well as position of traffic signs
and pedestrian crossings.
And one way to construct these maps
is to collect sensor data from many vehicles that
are equipped with sensors that can give a course
information about the position of the vehicle,
for example, the normal GPS system,
as well as sensors that detect and measure
for example, lane markings.
By collecting data from all vehicles that
have traveled a certain road, it is
possible to jointly estimate the vehicle's trajectories as well
as the map.
So an example is that you want to use the information
from the camera sensor at each time instance here
to accurately estimate the global position, heading,
and shape of all lanes.
So we want to store in the map a global map of all the lane
markings.
It can also include the global position
and shape of the guardrails, so a description of the guardrail.
We can also include the global position of signs
and what type of sign it is using image classification
to detect the sign type and using RADAR and or LIDAR to get
its position.
As we are not interested in having our estimate as fast as
possible, but are very interested in using
as much information as possible to make the map more
detailed and accurate, we can allow ourselves
to wait and collect as much data as we can
before we need to compute our densities.
Other examples of smoothing applications
are, for example, surveillance at airports
where it's important for safety reasons
to estimate the position of people and bags
and so forth, but without having a strong real-time requirement.
Here we are typically more interested in getting
an accurate understanding of what has happened.
And we can allow ourselves to collect more data in order
to be more certain and accurate.
Other examples include communication system
where we typically receive a complete message
before we want to decode it.
And by decoding it, we basically mean
that we want to estimate the message that was sent.
In sports, we want to, for example,
use a hawkeye system in tennis to determine if a tennis ball
was in or outside the line.
And we do this after the fact, by estimating
the trajectory of the ball using a complete set of images.
Other examples are in medicine where
we use a sequence of arterial blood pressure
to estimate the intercranial pressure.
Also here, it's more important to be accurate than timely.
Now let's look at when we are solving the prediction problem.
And again, we start with automotive applications.
So both our advanced driver assistance systems
and autonomous vehicles need to make predictions of the traffic
situation in the near future, when for example,
planning for a safe path or assessing collision risks.
And in both these cases, we need to have an understanding
of what will happen in the future
in order to take appropriate actions now.
And as we do not have any observation of the future yet,
we need to rely on predictions.
So for example, we would like to predict the relative position
and velocity of the other car.
So we want to know where these cars will be in the near future
in order to assess if we are going to collide with them
or in order to plan the path ahead.
We also would like to know relative position and heading
and shape of the current lane, such as when
we plan a path here in the future we
can stay within our own lane.
And similarly, it's interesting to know where the guardrail is
also in the future.
When it comes to predictions in other applications,
one example that most of us are familiar with
is weather predictions, where we want
to predict the winds and pressure and temperatures
for the coming days.
This also illustrates that it's always harder
to do predictions than filtering or smoothing,
where we have access to more data.
So it's hard to make these type of weather predictions,
at least in Sweden, where I live.
We have also other examples in economy
where the management of companies
relies on forecasts of, for example,
the demand of their products in order to make decisions.
And in politics, many decisions are
based on predictions regarding population
growth and the financial markets and so on.
So these are all examples of predictions that we do.
So here is a self-assessment question for you
to check your understanding of the difference
between these related problems.